<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The snare broken: or light discovering darknesse. Being an answer to a book intituled, Foot yet in the snare; published by James Naylor. Wherein his treachery and back-sliding from the true faith is brought to light, and his untrodden paths discovered. With some of his divided language and deceitful lyes in short laid open, and his spirit proved to be the same which appeared in all the false prophets, who say the Lord saith, when he spake not unto them; plainly to be seen by the impartial eye, in all those whose eyes are in their head, least the wolfe should devoure the lamb, under a shadow of love to the truth. / By a lover of truth and peace, called, John Toldervy.</title>
            <author>Toldervy, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94719</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1770</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E865_7</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866667</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866667</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168363</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94719)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168363)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 131:E865[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The snare broken: or light discovering darknesse. Being an answer to a book intituled, Foot yet in the snare; published by James Naylor. Wherein his treachery and back-sliding from the true faith is brought to light, and his untrodden paths discovered. With some of his divided language and deceitful lyes in short laid open, and his spirit proved to be the same which appeared in all the false prophets, who say the Lord saith, when he spake not unto them; plainly to be seen by the impartial eye, in all those whose eyes are in their head, least the wolfe should devoure the lamb, under a shadow of love to the truth. / By a lover of truth and peace, called, John Toldervy.</title>
                  <author>Toldervy, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for N. Brooks, and are to be sold at the Angel in Cornhil, and at the three Bibles neer the West end of Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Naylor, James.  Foot yet in the snare.</note>
                  <note>With a blank final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "January. 31 1655"; also the last number of the imprint date has been marked through and replaced with a 5.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660. --  Foot yet in the snare.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168363:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SNARE BROKEN: OR LIGHT diſcovering DARKNESSE. Being an anſwer to a Book entituled, <hi>FOOT yet in the SNARE;</hi> Publiſhed by <hi>JAMES NAYLOR.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein his treachery and back-ſliding from the true Faith is brought to Light, and his untrodden PATHS diſcovered.</p>
            <p>With ſome of his divided Language and deceitful Lyes in ſhort laid open, and his Spirit proved to be the ſame which appeared in all the falſe Prophets, who ſay the Lord ſaith, when he ſpake not unto them; plainly to be ſeen by the impartial eye, in all thoſe whoſe eyes are in their head, leaſt the Wolfe ſhould devoure the Lamb, under a ſhadow of love to the TRUTH.</p>
            <p>By a lover of Truth and Peace, called, <hi>John Toldervy.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſaiah 58.1.4.</hi>
               </bibl> Shew my people their tranſgreſſions, and the houſe of <hi>Jacob</hi> their ſins. Behold ye faſt for ſtrife and debate, and to ſmite with the fiſt of wickekneſſe, ye ſhall not faſt as ye do this day, to make your voice to be heard on high.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>James 2.1.</hi>
               </bibl> My Brethren, have not the Faith of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt the Lord of Glory, with reſpect of perſons.
<p>
                  <hi>In vain is the Snare laid in the ſight of any Bird.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>N. Brooks,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Angel in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> and at the three Bibles neer the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:168363:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168363:2"/>
            <head>The Snare broken: OR Light diſcovering Darkneſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OOD is the Word of the Lord, who by his Spirit hath foretold of the Heathen raging, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple fancying and imagining to themſelves vaine things, thereby to ſubdue the true appearance and exaltation of the King of Righteouſneſſe, in every age, of his coming into the world; who hath alſo foretold of ſuch, whoſe coming ſhould appear as the Angels of Light, (being transformed in the outward ſhape or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the Image of God) and in this his appearance, as a ſpecial end for the effecting of his bewitched deſign, he intrudes into the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of words, even words that are ſound and perfect, words of Life and Power, which came forth from the Spirit, whoſe way is truth, and whoſe end is life; but being ignorant of that Spirit from whence they came, they change them into fables, and ſo are become blaſphemers of that Immortal Seed by which they were brought to light: As alſo for the maintaining of their corrupt practiſe, (being not poſſeſſors of the perfect truth) they deſire to make a fair ſhow in the fleſh, and to that end they ſeek to give place to ſome Self-humility, that they may be diſtinguiſhed by men, that therein they may glory, as though in the ſufferings of Chriſt; but from that ſpirit and light in which there is no deceit, but the perfection of truth, let ſuch learne
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168363:3"/>reproof, and ſuffer rebuke, who boaſt of the Light to be their Guide, and yet are found in the Pit of Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ps, watching to afflict the children of my people, ſaith the Lord, and are ſearching ſecretly for a ſtumbling ſtone to caſt for a Rock of Offence in the ſtreets of the <hi>Holy Jeruſalem,</hi> even for a ſhelter for the accurſed ſeed, not only in thoſe who are brought into the way which guides to Salvation, and that have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in their knowledg a meaſure of the infallible truth, but alſo in ſuch who have ſomething of the ſimplicity ariſing to life in them, by which they are guided in love to ſeek after the way of truth, if that for <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> ſake they might come to know where they might find the ſufferings of the Croſſe, for the reſtoration of the Righteous Seed, which maketh free the City of God.</p>
            <p>But the Word of Scripture hath foretold, that ſuch Hereſies and Schiſmes muſt be in the Church, that the approved of the Lord might be made manifeſt; and now it will plainly appear to thoſe who are in any meaſure of the Light and Faith of Chriſt, ſuch a one hath been found in that blaſphemous work, the Anſwer of that Book ſet forth by me, entituled, <hi>The Foot out of the Snare;</hi> for that from the root of bitterneſs and envy, there is brought to light a bundle of unclean ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomous things, and filthy deceitful lies, confuſion, and raſhneſs, in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil ſpeaking againſt the truth, yet notwithſtanding are they all ſought to be juſtified in the deepeſt ſubtilty of the Serpent, by going about to intrap the ſimple mind, with much uſing thoſe words which were ſpoken from the ſimplicity in ſuch a life, for ſuch an end, that he which abides in a lye knoweth not.</p>
            <p>Now unto ſuch, who for a perſwaſion, have and do ſatisfie themſelves in things, which thoſe that are by them judged to be before them in the faith, doth believe and declare for truth; unto ſuch, I ſay, read and ſee your vanity, for herein is the Deceiver greatly upheld, you being not eye-witneſſes to what you believe in your ſelves; and though the Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and you people are both joyned in one to ſpeak againſt imitation, yet in your hearts are you both confederate in this whoredome, and birth of fornication, in that the one imagines and frames in his mind a certain belief that what is ſpoken from the other muſt be true, rooted and grounded in him from a perſwaſion in himſelf, that his Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is in the enjoyment of the <hi>Covenants,</hi> in the Redemption and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed poſſeſſion of the Blood of the Lamb, a ſpiritual man moved and guided to ſpeak in, by, and from the Spirit; and the other, which is the leader, concludes in himſelf, that ſuch a belief in a weak Brother, who is not yet come to that meaſure of Spirit or Reſurrection of Life
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:168363:3"/>with himſelf, is in the faith and power of truth; <hi>but for this cauſe many are ſick, and weak, and many ſleep.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who is there in whom there is any knowledg that will not condemn this Faith, the Truth in this practiſe, of taking things upon truſt, being ſold for Uſury: The Spirit of God ſaith, <hi>Follow us, as we follow Chriſt;</hi> but it doth not ſay, <hi>Follow us, becauſe we believe, or do ſo;</hi> but herein, thou who art in this practiſe, art witneſſed to be in the corrupt nature, in ſelf-worſhip, where all the blind guides in the world are leading ſilly people, who know not the perfect wayes of truth, to ſay as they ſay, and do as they do, though the end of ſuch a worſhip is death.</p>
            <p>And for thee <hi>James Naylor,</hi> thy madneſſe and folly is made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in what thou haſt done, and thy vain deceit diſcovered, yet not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Adultereſſe eye, but unto that light which is of God, the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Truth againſt Deceit in all conſciences, and thy Troops of Lyes, which are ſheltered under thy great ſwelling words of vanity, are here laid open before thee, and turned back again to their own habitation, even into thy own boſome; and though thy envy had a reſpect to what ſcandal and reproach thou couldeſt caſt upon me, on purpoſe that thou mighteſt make me to appear odious, yet do I not va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue thy deceit therein, neither am I in the leaſt disſatisfied as to my perſon, yet ſorrow and a lamentation there hath been, becauſe of what evil thou haſt brought upon thy ſelf, and that truth which thou pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeſt, and alſo the effects which that Spirit thou haſt appeared in might accompliſh upon ſuch, whom otherwiſe might have learned wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from that plain ſimple mind which appeared in me, in what I have diſcovered: Have I ſpoken in ſoberneſſe, and dealt moderately, and have I therein ſmitten the truth? How is it thou would'ſt have had me to a ſpoken? Can Truth ſpeak but its own? Had I appeared a Tranſgreſſor of the Law, like to thy ſelf, with a rebellious provoking ſpirit, then mighteſt thou have juſtly reproved me; but now for this thy uncleanneſſe (it being a work of thy ſelf) know this, that Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will reſt upon thee, for that I gave thee divers Cauſions, yet haſt thou rebelled againſt knowledg; but now henceforwards learne from this thy weakneſſe, to ceaſe from raſhneſſe, and not to run be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that light, of which thou declareſt to be thy perfection, for thou art no more the Miniſter of Circumciſion, for the crucifying of the body, and the aboliſhing of fleſh, I ſay, no longer then thou abide in the Faith thy ſelf; but thou art become the Miniſter of Circumciſion, for the ſervice of the outward Law of words.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:168363:4"/>
            <p>But to examine and ſearch thy work, the Foundation, and the end thereof.</p>
            <p>Thou beginneſt with a diſcourſe to we Nine, calling us the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then raging, of which the Spirit of the Lord foretold, and that we imagine vain things, and ſo ſtop the appearance and exaltation of the King of Righteouſneſſe in this Age; and that we are <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> who battel againſt the Lamb, which Lamb thou ſayeſt is in thee, (though here thou wilt be found a lyar, and inſtead of a Lamb will appear a Wolfe) Then thou calleſt us Subtilty, Sorcerers, and Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crafts, who are of the devil; and that we hate Innocency; and ſo thou goeſt on, calling us the Deceived, and the bewitched of the Devil, with lyes. and lying wonders, joyning together head and tail, root and branch, in that nature, to trample upon the appearance of Chriſt, and ſhut up the Kingdome againſt men; and thou goeſt on, calling me the Child of Perdition; and after much more ſuch kind of ſtuff which thou ſpeakeſt of me, thou calleſt me a <hi>Judas,</hi> and thoſe who put their hands to my book, thou ſayeſt they are the Chief Prieſts; and ſo thou goeſt on, calling us the Dragon and the Beaſt, with the many Heads and Horns, with Blaſphemy on every Head, and that my book is blaſphemy; and then thou ſayeſt, it doth now appear ſo to be, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as thou haſt not witneſſed from truth one word of blaſphemy in the whole book. All theſe, and many more filthy, corrupt, and deceitfull lyes (in reſpect of that work which is in hand) (as may be ſeen by the impartial eye, in all thoſe whoſe eyes are in their head, if obſerving the following diſcourſe) being laid as a Foundation for thy bewitched end, thou preſenteſt them before three ſorts of perſons, whom thou ſayeſt are much concerned in what we Nine have hatched and brought forth; (calling it a filthy thing) which blaſphemous lye thou waſt forewarned of before, as I have ſaid, not only in my book, but alſo ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified to thy face when we ſpake together; and for inſtance, thou mayeſt well remember the firſt work thou waſt guided in, when after I was known to thee, was in much ſubtilty to ſearch what thou couldeſt get forth of me, as touching this, and alſo concerning other matters which reſpected the Miniſters, which being ſeen, I refuſed thy ſpirit, for which thou had'ſt not a word to ſpeak, but did reſt ſilent: Mayeſt thou not bluſh for ſhame, for that thou ſhouldeſt dare to appear in ſlandering of ſo many perſons after ſo groſſe a manner as thou haſt here done, to the view of all the world? O thou Corruption! doſt thou boaſt of the Law? <hi>Through breaking the Law diſhonoreſt thou God, for the Name of God is now blaſphemed among the Heathen, through
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168363:4"/>you;</hi> for as I have ſaid, thy Circumciſion profits not, while as yet thou art found in the tranſgreſſion; and here is <hi>Core,</hi> who came forth of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and yet gainſaid, thinkeſt thou it will ſerve thy turn to ſay, thy thoughts were ſo, and now to ſay thou wilt do ſo no more; nay, it will not, but thy reward ſhall abide ſhame and diſhonor which thou haſt brought upon thy ſelfe, and that truth which thou profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt.</p>
            <p>Thou goeſt forwards in thy deſign, and for a better incouragement of thy end towards thoſe three ſorts of perſons, &amp;c. and for a further diſcovery of thy malice towards the Miniſters, in thy haſte thou haſt reproved them for witneſſing the truth, which thou denieſt not; but thy deceit calleth it the Devils actings: true that relation which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares of thoſe effects, which a deluded ſpirit wrought in and upon me, under a pretence of light, that ſpeaks of the Devils actings, and for that cauſe were they diſcovered, becauſe they were the Devils actings, who is a Lyar from the beginning, and abode not in the truth, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth he abide in the truth, and thoſe works of the Devil were diſcovered for that end, that the nature and the effects thereof might anſwer to the good of others; yet dareſt thou ſay, that thoſe who are in the leaſt meaſure of the light, ſeeth this deed to be a ſecret ſmiting againſt the juſt; but thou art denied, and that light by which thou ſpeakeſt, for that by which they were brought to light, was Life.</p>
            <p>Having thus made a preparation by thy lying ſpirit, in the uſing of thoſe words of Scripture which were ſpoken in knowledge, for a true end by thoſe who writ them, thinking thereby to darken the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, thou goeſt forwards in thy ſixth <hi>Page,</hi> directing thy mind to us all, giving us to know from thy beſotted and ſelf-will mind, that we all are joyned to bear witneſſe to confuſions and lying wonders, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting us that we turn to the light of Chriſt, and take notice againſt whom we are joyned therein, which light thou ſayeſt hath appeared in thee, and may be ſeen by us in this thy work, of laying open lyes, confuſions, and lying wonders, and then thou goeſt on, bearing witneſſe againſt thy ſelf, ſaying, that we never ſaw it, or heard it, and confirmeſt what thou ſo ſpeakeſt with another lye, ſaying, that we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo confeſſed what thou ſpeakeſt to be true. Now if thy ſaying here were true, how is it that I could have written it, or any of thoſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters appeared in it? but this I ſhall bear with, judging it to be a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, and if thou had'ſt judged in righteouſneſſe, and not according to a ſeeming appearance, as thou couldeſt not otherwiſe be convinced in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168363:5"/>thy ſelf, concerning thoſe words ſpoken by the Miniſters, which are leſs in a miſtake then theſe here of thine, then thou couldeſt not have been found in this work, but with the light of which thou ſpeakeſt thy cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt judgment, and filthy nature, is here ſeen, their words ſpeak of a ſad and remarkable providence, to which they give witneſſe, which words are the ſum of all that their mind and meaning did ſignifie, witneſſe by the light in thy own conſcience, for thou knoweſt well they are ſtrangers in their judgment to all thoſe things diſcovered by me, as yours, as alſo divers of thoſe diſcovered, as mine; but were they not thoſe words, <hi>A ſad and remarkable,</hi> may not have any reſpect to any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular contained in the book, but that ſcope and matter which diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers thoſe wiles and ſubtilties, which from time to time I was inſnared in by the evil ſpirit, together with what providence attended me, while under thoſe temptations; but yet to me there is a miſtake, which I ſeek not to juſtifie, which thy malice againſt knowledge hath taken hold on.</p>
            <p>So thou goeſt on in contradiction to thy former words, repeating ſome of thoſe words which the Miniſters have put their hands unto, which ſpeaks, that ſome of them have perſued a part of my writings, which thou denieſt not, but believeſt; and then thou goeſt on, reproving them for their tenderneſſe in ſo ſpeaking, and for bearing witneſſe to what I had declared touching the nature of thoſe workes which the evill ſpirit guided me in ſubjection unto; and yet, as I have ſaid, there is not one word in thy whole booke, which beareth witneſs againſt what thou haſt reproved them for, but for the anſwering of thy end, thou ſayeſt I am one poſſeſſed with a deluded ſpirit; then if ſo, how is it that the light and Spirit of Chriſt hath here appeared, in laying open thy deceit, but thy words and their end are ſeen; yet it is true, time was that I was poſſeſſed with a deluded ſpirit, even exeedingly poſſeſſed, but now great is my peace, yea great is my peace, the Lord having wrought for his Name ſake a deliverance for his choſen, and hath made knowne his Election, praiſes to his Name for ever.</p>
            <p>Thou ſayeſt further, that we are found falſifying our owne words, and ſo have inſnared our ſelves in our own wickedneſſe, and this we call, <hi>The Foot out of the Snare.</hi> Thus directing thy mind to us all, whereas not one of them had the leaſt knowledg of the Title, or any particular contained in the Epiſtle, untill it came forth to the ſight of the world, and ſo thou ſayeſt our worke is begun with a lye, and ſo carried on, who in our title page (ſpeaking in a lye, thy mind being to us all) tell of the manner of my ſeparation from the <hi>Quakers,</hi> which as thou ſayeſt is falſe,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168363:5"/>(ſpeaking in theſe words) that thoſe we call <hi>Quakers</hi> did ſeparate from me, and denied me both in word and writing, becauſe of my following a bewitched ſpirit, and would not be reclaimed by you, who often reproved and judged me for it with one conſent; and then for a witneſſe to what thou haſt ſpoken, thou goeſt to the latter part of my book to borrow a proof from my words to bear thee up, but think not to juſtifie thy ſelf with lies, which thou canſt not witneſſe; for from that time of my firſt compliance with you, untill about a week before that time which the evil ſpirit guided me in that bewitched ſervice of i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitating the crucifying of Chriſt, I ſay, from that time until this time, of which I ſpeak, there was not one word of reproof given unto me by any one of them, but great tenderneſſe and love they bear towards me, by which may clearly be ſeen, that there was great hopes in them concerning me, yea, and there was great hopes of me, for that they obſerved my zeal and faithfulneſſe in that work I was called unto, for which I received from them great incouragement, but whether or no the nature of the greateſt part of thoſe temptations, which are rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in my book, with many more, was known unto them, I cannot ſay; and whereas thou ſayeſt, that any of you did ſeparate from me, or deny me in word or writing, becauſe I would not be reclaimed by them, it is true they did deny me, and ſo I have ſaid in my book, that they did deny me, and that becauſe I would not be reclaimed by them; but as thy own words ſpeak in contradiction to what thou ſayeſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I did deny them firſt, yet not with a bewitched ſpirit, and what I then did deny, I deny ſtill: which deed in me is true, and abides, yea, and will abide, when thy vanity (if I may ſo call it) in thoſe things which thou reſpecteſt, as worſhip to God, wherein is emptineſs and nothingneſſe, when I ſay this thy vanity ſhall ceaſe, and this do I ſpeak in a good conſcience, except thy knowledge is yet before mine, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of thoſe things of which thou mayeſt underſtand that I now ſpeak of.</p>
            <p>So thou goeſt on with a lye (in reſpect of the Miniſters) ſaying, that we told of what judgment I was learned in by the Miniſtery of thoſe people, (meaning your ſelves) and ſo we bear witneſſe we know not to what; for that thou ſayeſt, that both they (ſpeaking of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter) and I, am yet unlearned in the judgment and Miniſtery of thoſe we call <hi>Quakers,</hi> and yet in thy fifteenth page, after thou haſt repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed much of what I have ſpoken, thou confeſſeſt that they were preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous truths, and alſo that I have diſcovered in my book of many more precious truths, which neerly concernes the ſalvation of every ſoule;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168363:6"/>and in thy 22. and 37. page, thou denieſt not, but that I was reſtored again by the true light, from that ſad and loſt condition which I was in, and that afterwards I was guided in that obedience which was profeſſed by the <hi>Quakers:</hi> but this it may be thou waſt perſwaded to make uſe of 'for that it concerned thee for the anſwering of thy end, in reſpect of what thou ſpeakeſt in thy following diſcourſe; yet here thy end is ſeen, thou art made manifeſt, thy blindneſſe and thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion is brought to light, Dareſt thou ſay that light guided thee in this thy work? ſilence for ſhame, ſilence thy ſelfe, untill thou canſt ſpeak in plainneſſe with a true mind, and a right underſtanding.</p>
            <p>Thou goeſt on with thy lye ſaying, that in our Epiſtle, we ſay the ſubject matter of our diſcourſe relates principally to the perſons, who go under the Name of <hi>Quakers,</hi> whereas (as I have before ſpoken) not one of them had any knowledge of any one particular contained therein, untill it came forth to the ſight of the world.</p>
            <p>Then thou goeſt forward, repeating many words, ſaying, We con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that many have abuſed the truth, by ſeeking to defend themſelves in that deceit, which that Spirit which is of God in thoſe we call <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> have witneſſed againſt; I ſay that word, we call as to me, is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach.</p>
            <p>So you go forwards with my words, which ſpeaks, that the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p of men are already beyond meaſure bitterly incenſed againſt you, for which tenderneſſe and ſimplicity of mind, which reſpects an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to you, thou replieſt with a reproof, ſaying. Let our practiſe judge us as to the thing in hand, confirming thy reproof with a lye, (ſo far as it is known to me) ſaying, That we ſeek to defend our ſelves in that deceit, which the Spirit of God in you have witneſſed againſt, and ſo hath made thy ſelfe manifeſt, to be one of thoſe who have abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the truth, of which thou ſayeſt, It is thy Guide. And whereas thou goeſt on, ſaying, That the devil had never ſuch a deſign on foot, for the incenſing of people againſt you, as my book; I ſay thou art found herein witneſſed to be the Liar, from thy own words, in that thou doſt acknowledge in thy 23. and 27. pages, and in other places of thy paper, that I have oftentimes in my book cleared you from preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice. Again, thou reproveſt us, that we are not aſhamed in that we ſay the ſubject matter doth relate principally to you, which thou ſayeſt was acted amongſt us, who are joyned on in it againſt that Spirit of God in the <hi>Quakers,</hi> by which it was denied in the perſons of them, both root and branch thereof, as thou ſayeſt is confeſſed and witneſſed by us: To which I ſay, for the Miniſters, they are not concerned there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168363:6"/>and for what I have ſo ſpoken, I am not aſhamed, for it doth and may concerne them, and alſo others beſides them, for hath God made knowne his judgments, and ſhewed his power upon me, for that I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from the truth, and gave heed unto lying vanities, by which ſorrow and miſerie did befall me, and the ſeed of the righteous became deſolate: and did this evill befall me while I was amongſt you? and have I now plainly, as from the Lord, diſcovered the nature thereof, he having ſhewed unto me the cauſe and the end thereof? and have I now ſhewed unto you and to the world the true cauſe and the end, that ſo ſuch who are of you unſetled in their minds, or unfaithful in their work towards the Lord, might thereby learn to feare, and to be kept ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the love and faith which is profeſſed? which end thou makeſt of what I have writ unto them thy ſelf; nay, did'ſt thou ever ſee any thing that might ſerve more for cauſion, or reproof, to ſuch who are of your ſelves, then this, are you here accuſed? then underſtand, wherein and wherein you are accuſed: I ſay, ſee if you may not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in learn reproof, but you are not only accuſed, but you are excuſed, where it is yours, and where truth abides, there it is ſeen; and alſo thy deceit hath confeſſed the ſame, as from what I have ſpoken in many places of my book, though other things in the ſame deceit thou haſt changed into lyes, (but that is for thy deſign) So (in thine own words) I ſay, let all now judge who have the ſpirit of truth, if thou art not one of thoſe miſguided ſpirits, who ſtand up in defence of deceit againſt the Spirit of Truth, that thereby thou mighteſt caſt a ſtumbling block in the plain way of the Lord, that ſo his people might be ſtayed in the midſt thereof; and let your work judge you who have taken part with your deceit acted between your ſelves, in deſpite to the Spirit of God.</p>
            <p>Thou goeſt further, ſaying, that <hi>Judas</hi> and the Chief Prieſts might as truly charge what they did in combination together againſt Chriſt, upon the eleven Diſciples, as we charge our act and combination up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the perſons of you, or the Spirit of God in you; unto which, I ſay, a lye ſpeaks, for our act and combination it was not, neither have I charged what is ſpoken, upon you, or the ſpirit of God in you, but where any thing that I have writ doth gainſay the evil ſpirit that is in any of you, that is yours, and good is it that you have ſeen a viſitation thereby.</p>
            <p>Again, thou ſayeſt, that in our Epiſtle we tell of expreſſing tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe towards our Brethren, yea, and I do ſo ſay, tenderneſſe towards my Brethren, who are miſguided in their ſpirits, ſubjected under Laws and Traditions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which ſtands in the invention, by which they are covered in deceit, and through their weakneſſe they are led forth,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168363:7"/>denying themſelves what is juſt and lawful in the ſight of God; and this they do through fear, in flaverie to the Prince of deceit.</p>
            <p>Thou goeſt on, directing thy falſe mind in a confuſed manner to us all, whereas thy ſcope, by what I can underſtand, reflects upon the Miniſters; and then in thy 9. page, thou ſayeſt, as for the denying our ſelves liberty, lawful or unlawful, we are little guiltie of that crime; ſayeſt thou ſo, then thy accuſation is ceaſed; for if we deny not lawful li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, then are we in the Redemption, in which Faith our work ſhall abide; (but I plead not to juſtifie the fleſh) yet for my own part, am I free, or not free, it is far ſhort of thy knowledge. But here thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſteſt thy confuſion and contradictions, for if any part of what the Law requireth be overcome by that which is without Law, then is the requirings of Law denied, or if any part of what is without Law be ſubdued by the requiring of the Law, then is it, that what is without Law is denied; but if thou ſayeſt in thy follie, that we denie not the requiring of the Law, as thy words muſt ſpeak, otherwiſe they muſt ſpeak perfectly on the contrarie, then I ſay thy whole book was ſpoke in and from a lie, and there is nothing more but confuſions, ſo thou goeſt forwards in thy own by-way; and then thou ſpeakeſt of change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able faſhions, and fooliſh childiſh toys in our habits, which thou ſayeſt we are pleading for, whereas there is no ſuch matter in any one word contained in my whole book.</p>
            <p>In thy 10. page, thou demandeſt what libertie you are charged to denie, I ſay, that libertie denied by you, of which I ſpake, may plainly be ſeen by what I have alreadie ſpoken in my former: You tell again of what I ſpake, in that I would give an accompt of my ſeparation from you, which thou denieſt, but that lie thou here ſpokeſt on is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready returned whence it came; for I firſt did ſeparate from you, as I have ſaid, the manner of which is diſcovered in my former book.</p>
            <p>Thou goeſt forwards doting in thy lie, ſpeaking to the Miniſters, ſaying, that in their cauſion to the Reader, they confeſſe, that my er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, from what was written in the Scripture, and in my ſelf, was that by which I deeply ſuffered, and ſayeſt thou, that before we have caſt it on the perſons of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> whereas (as before is wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed) there is no ſuch thing; but here thou art found with that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit in thy own mouth, which thou caſteſt upon us.</p>
            <p>In thy 14. page thou repeateſt my words, which ſpeaks, that I have been for divers years full of zeal after the things of God, ſeeking after the knowledg of Chriſt; and then (for the anſwering of thy end) thou
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168363:7"/>skippeſt over divers lines, leaving the ſcope and true meaning of what is related, contained in thoſe words, <hi>I was perſwaded;</hi> and ſo thou bringeſt my words ſpoken in another place, with purpoſe to ſhew a contradiction in me. When thus thou haſt confounded thy ſelfe, in leaving out thoſe words which ſpeaks the truth of my mind: Then in the cloſe of the ſame page, for thy purpoſe, thou repeateſt theſe words, <hi>Wayes moſt uſeful,</hi> but leaves out the word <hi>perſwaded.</hi> And having thus done, thou requireſt of us to tell thee, if all that cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of it may not ſee us ſtart blind and drunk with abomination and confuſion: To which I anſwer, no, they may not; for having, here conſidered and tried thy ſpirit, they may ſee plainlie, that the blinde and drank with abomination and confuſion is thy ſelfe: Then thou makeſt thy Application upon this thy own confuſion unto us, ſaying, <hi>Can wayes moſt uſefull</hi> (leaving out the word <hi>perſwaded</hi>) for clearing my <hi>Conſcience,</hi> in order to my upright and cloſe walking with God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and reſting in much fleſhlie wiſdome and glorying, in being co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with deceit, ſtand together in one perſon: To which I anſwer the perverter of truth no, neither have I ſaid any ſuch thing as thou here charge us with; for if thou believeſt my ſaying, that I was cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed over with deceit, and reſted in much fleſhlie wiſdome, then thou mayeſt clearlie ſee, that it is thy work, and not ours, which cannot ſtand together. For was not <hi>Paul</hi> led forth verie ſtrict in zeal, and as touching the Law blameleſſe, and was he not perſwaded that therein he was the ſervant of God, for the clearing of his conſcience, but yet notwithſtanding this, when he came trulie to ſee his condition, he ſaw his ſtrictneſſe of zeal, his ſervice of the Law, and his perſwaſion therein; to be all fleſhlie and carnal, which kind of worſhip we have too much amongſt us; and theſe things are not unknown to thee, yet thou gainſayeſt this teſtimonie, and thou reproveſt the Miniſters for their tenderneſſe; in ſaying ſome of them read it all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
            <p>In thy 12. page, thou repeateſt apart of my words in thy owne way, and leaveſt out others, as thou did'ſt before, ſpeaking of a ſpirit which I ſaid was infuſed in me, by the opperation whereof, together with what I apprehended of my ſelfe; after a ſhort time there was made cleare to my underſtanding what followes. Having thus in thy confuſed way ſpoken thy mind and meaning contrarie to mine, thou goeſt forwards, ſaying; That we confeſſe this ſpirit from which I had thoſe apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, was infuſed into me before I knew the <hi>Quakers:</hi> After which, (ſayeſt thou) I became affected with thoſe people called <hi>Seekers,</hi> and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168363:8"/>afterwards met with two of thoſe called <hi>Quakers,</hi> and yet the drift of thy book is to make people believe that I received this ſpirit amongſt the <hi>Quakers;</hi> and ſo thou ſayeſt we have cleared you, (ſpeaking in a lye) of that we intended for ſlander; but to prove thy work, my words thou mayeſt ſee ſpeak thus, with reſpect to you, where I ſay, by whoſe doctrine (together with what I apprehended of my ſelf) by the opperation of a ſpirit infuſed into me after a ſhort time, &amp;c. And then I ſay, that firſt I ſhall declare the manner of my enterance into this Belief, which manner of enterance may be ſeen plainly (as is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by that word firſt) to be the door, through and by which I was guided to that belief before ſpoken; ſo that the infuſed ſpirit, of which I ſpake, was not before, but after I knew the <hi>Quakers,</hi> which ſnare I was caught in by their words, through conſulting with my ſelf; ſo that here thou ſhalt ſee, that this piece of confuſion thou haſt caſt upon us is thy own.</p>
            <p>Again, thou goeſt on with thy former deceit, ſpeaking part of my words, and laying aſide others to ſerve thy end, ſaying, That I tell of the <hi>Quakers</hi> that which they ſpake was againſt all ſin, yet they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered nothing of the Myſterie of the Goſpel of Chriſt, which is falſe, for what is true ſpeak not ſo, but as it is related it was my wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which word <hi>Wiſdome</hi> thou haſt here left out, and in divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places of thy book, for others of thy falſe ends, thou haſt own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the word, and made uſe thereof; and for that I ſaid they ſpake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all ſin, it is true they did ſo ſpeak, but their words were few ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken after this manner, lye not, deceive not, let your words be yea and nay, deal truly with God and man, and ſuch like expreſſions, that are one and the ſame with the Scripture thou ſpeakeſt on, which ſaith, <hi>Sin no more, leſt a worſe thing come upon thee;</hi> which manner of ſpeaking, as I have ſaid, I concluded in my wiſdome to come ſhort of the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of Chriſt; ſo that here we, which thou chargeſt with a lye, ſtand free, and thoſe words which I ſpake withall witneſs that the Lie is thine own; canſt thou look upon thy unclean work of deceit which thou haſt formed againſt us, and not learn reproof? What boldneſs canſt thou have to appear hereen? Is this from the Lord? Or is it not from thy own wilful corruption, when thou ſhalt take part of my words; to carry on the deſign of a lye in enmity againſt us, and leave the other part, by which we are juſtified in the truth, and thou condemned in the work of thy lie, yea, ſurely it is ſo, and ſo own it as the work of thy corruption.</p>
            <p>In thy 13. page (ſpeaking to the Miniſters) thou ſayeſt, they tell
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168363:8"/>of one vvhom I knevv to be a very ſerious true-hearted man vvhich vvas converted to your belief, vvhich gave me to underſtand, that the perſon, that Son of God vvhich dyed at Jeruſalem, vvas not the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer of man from ſin.</p>
            <p>All which in thy meaning I denie; for (as before is witneſſed) they ſaid not ſo, but I ſaid ſo, and if thou wilt ſo have it, they witneſſed me in ſo ſpeaking, and not I them; and for that, I ſay, he gave me to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that the perſon, that Son of God that dyed at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> was not the Redeemer of man from ſin; it is true in the words themſelves, but not (as I ſay) in thy meaning, which thing alſo in the cloſe of this Page, thou haſt both confeſſed and denied thy ſelf, ſaying, That all which ever knew you wil bear you witneſs, that you own no Redeemer but that Son of God which died at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> whom, ſay you, we witneſs in us, the Light by which you ſee ſin, and by obedience thereto are led out of ſin.</p>
            <p>If thy words here, ſpeaking of the Son of God, reſpects the ſpirit of that perſon which died at <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> (as I judge it doth) then may thy ſaying be underſtood in thoſe words, <hi>We witneſs him a light in us, &amp;c.</hi> for in him dwelleth fulneſs of the Godhead, by which fulneſs of his have all thoſe who have lived in his Light received grace for grace: Now if this be thy meaning, then have I witneſs from thy ſelf, for what is diſcovered touching the perſon of that Son of God which died at Jeruſalem; but if thy meaning muſt be taken as thou haſt ſaid, then thy words are not, for that what they ſpeak cannot be; but now witneſſed by thy ſelf we are not ſlanderers, nor backbiters, neither doth that perſon deſerve admonition which ſpake the words; yet if thou wouldſt know his name from me, though I judg thou art not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant who it was, it was <hi>Simon Dring,</hi> who meeting with me in the ſtreet, at the head of <hi>Bartlemy-Lane</hi> behinde the Exchange, had ſome conference with me, the effects whereof (as could remember) I have declared.</p>
            <p>In thy 14. page thou ſayeſt I ſeem to reproach you, in that I ſay ſome of you faſted 30. or 40. daies; I ſay, the words themſelves ſpeak no ſuch thing, neither is it my mind, but-as ſuch a work was this diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for a ſign, according as thy ſelf hath applied.</p>
            <p>Thou goeſt further in this page, telling of thoſe two ſpirits which was in me, one contrary to the other, by which I did many things in my will againſt my wil, and then thou skippeſt to the end of my book, where I ſay, before I was perſwaded to comply with you, I had a right Knowledge of your belief and practiſe, and then ſayeſt thou here is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168363:9"/>piece of my confuſion manifeſted, and for a proof thereof, thou goeſt to the end of that relation, which declares of what deluſions I was in, where I have ſaid that I was judged by you; and when thou haſt thus blinded the truth, by this thy own work of deſpight, and ſo the confuſion thy own; thou calleſt us falfe Witneſſes which cannot agree together in our Work, but who is there that may not ſee thy vain mind and the falſe Witneſs of which thou ſpeakeſt, which cannot agree in one to be in thy ſelf; ceaſe for ſhame, ceaſe from diſturbing the truth, and perverting the right minde of the Lord; have I in ſimplicity declared the way by which I came to be loſt and ſo enſnared by the deceiver, that his Way and Works being laid open, it might anſwer to the benefit of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and yet goeſt thou about to make uſe thereof for by-ends, and to caſt a ſtumbling block before what good might otherwiſe be learned thereby; look upon thy work, and behold thy end; I ſay, as I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared before, I had a right knowledge of your belief and practiſe, but when coming to be guided by what I had learned in my underſtanding, that fiery zeal of which I ſpake, being in my will, brought in darkneſs upon my ſpirit, by which darkneſs I was overcome to do many things in my will againſt my will, and for reproof from any of you I received none; until that time I have before mentioned; and here as to what thou haſt ſpoken, thou art left without excuſe, being witneſſed againſt by the Light of Chriſt; which thou ſayeſt we have accuſed, and the unſavoury ſtuff it is thy own, which thy ſlandering ſpirit have caſt forth of the bottomeleſs pit.</p>
            <p>In thy 15. page thou ſayeſt, I tell of my believing, that what was manifeſted of God in man, was the Light of life, and one with himſelf, and that man was the cauſe of all his diſtractions and confuſions in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and that man having loſt the Kernall and Subſtance, he feedeth on dry husks, and being not refreſhed with Bread and Water of Life, he remaineth alwaies ſeeking and never ſatisfied, and that eternall life li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in us, there needs no more thirſts; &amp;c. And having thus done, thou confeſſeſt they, and many more which thou haſt not mentioned, are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious truths, and ſayeſt thou, theſe being things which the devill moſt envie, we (ſpeaking in a lye) have mixed with them ſome of our ovvn de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, thereby the better to make people believe they are errors; to which I ſay, why didſt not thou declare thoſe errors, that ſo I might have ſeen my weakneſs, and the people have learned Knowledge; but here thou exclaimeſt againſt the truth, and ſtayeſt at home to cover thy deceit; but this is to carry on thy deſigne amongſt thoſe who ſay as thou ſayeſt, diſcovered in thoſe words, We ſtrike at the whole foundation at once,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168363:9"/>after which ſubtile deſigne, thou repeateſt a part of my Words, which ſpeaks another thing, and relates to another end, then vvhat is before diſcovered contained in thoſe Words, I ſhall declare ſome of thoſe ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects vvhich this change vvrought in me, and having ſo done, thou skippeſt to the end of my Relation, confounding thy ſelf in not obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the ſcope and order of my Words, and there repeateſt the crucify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of my ſelf, and burning my leg, and pricking needles in my thumbs, and ſuch like, which thy ſubtilty calls bewitched ſtuff, though it is true it was (as I have ſo called it) bewitched ſtuff, haddeſt not thou dealt fairlie and trulie with thy ſelf, and with me alſo, in taking the ſcope and order of my writing, as things were diſcovered, have I not ſaid thoſe temptations overpowred me at my firſt entrance, occaſioned by the fire of my zeal, and that afterwards, when I came to ſee my folly, I was reſtored to a right underſtanding of what was true, which thing thou haſt acknowledged in divers places of thy book, in owning my words, which ſpeaks, that I was guided in that obedience which was profeſſed by you; if then I make a difference between that obedience you profeſſed, and that practiſe I was guided in, while under thoſe temptations, which I have done in many places, then I ſay where art thou in this thy work? if not drunk with new Wine, and ſmothered in the dark Clouds of the miſty day, behold confuſion upon confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, is <hi>Babilon</hi> overcome, is <hi>Babilon</hi> ceaſed, when ſo many langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, voices, and ſounds breaks forth, and diſcover themſelves in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacie againſt the ſimplicitie of truth, yet will not my people ſee theſe things, ſaith the Lord; but though they will not ſee, yet will I go up to the Mountain of my holineſſe, and there will I plead for my Name ſake, that if may be the reſtorer might comfort <hi>Zion,</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> my glory might ſee their deliverer.</p>
            <p>Thou goeſt on with my words, which ſpeaks, that I was guided not to pluck off my hat to any man, to ſpeak the words <hi>Thee</hi> and <hi>Thou,</hi> not to bow to any man, not to direct my mind in drinking to any, to pull off my points at the knees, and my buttons which were unneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary; and ſuch like things which thou ſayeſt we would loath, ſee go down, and therefore give it, as though it was the ſpirit of the devil, which bear witneſſe againſt them, and ſo we would condemn the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, and practiſe of the Saints, to which I ſay thou art denied in what is ſpoken; for that cauſe and end for which thoſe things were diſcovered, was to ſhew the raſhneſſe and forwardneſſe of my zeal, by which I was guided in all thoſe things without the ſpirit of God; and though the ſpirit of God ſhould witneſſe the deniall of all thoſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168363:10"/>things in another, (which I can yet ſcarce believe) yet, I ſay, in that my haſtie work of denying them, it was not of God but of the devil, and let ſuch who are found in the practiſe of them, ſee if the ſame ſpirit be not the ground of their practiſe; yet do I not judge, for judgement is committed to the Son, whoſe light is in you all, but for pride and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs I reſt ſilent, directing that moderation might be our guide, and for a moderation in all thoſe things, I find not the ſpirit of God any where witneſs againſt: But thou ſayeſt I am a <hi>Judas,</hi> for that I have betrayed thy Light, and ſo I cannot ſee, being over-ſhadowed with darkneſs: Wel, is it ſo? am I a <hi>Judas?</hi> then it is unto thee; for that what I have betrayed is thy Light; if then this thy Light be darkneſs, my work is true; yet however thy Light, as touching what we have before ſpoken, is darkneſs to mine, and for that I have done, and do, my conſcience beareth me witneſs in the ſight of God, which otherwiſe were I a <hi>Judas</hi> a burden would reſt upon me; but know this, I have ſeene the end of things, and have learned to ceaſe from man; and if for theſe things thou ſmiteſt at us, becauſe I call my work, <hi>The Foot out of the Snare; or, a reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Inhabitants of Zion into their place;</hi> then is it that truth is cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, for it is not, that <hi>Zion</hi> the Citie of the Lord was laine waſt, and the inhabitants thereof diſperſed to the ends of the earth, was not the Mountain of the houſe of the Lord laid low, and the inhabitable parts of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> made deſolate; yea ſurelie, and a great crie and lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there was for the deſolation of her people; but now the everlaſting Father of love in time hath made known his power, by which delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance hath been wrought for his Name ſake, praiſes, praiſes to his name for ever: And as touching thoſe things before ſpoken, I have given in my witneſs alreadie, they are no ſnare unto me, yet do I not boaſt in them, for that I know much temptation attends upon them, therefore I direct to all, as I have done before, wait for a moderation, for the righteous Judge is in his work, and by your deeds you muſt be proved, and not by words, and your reward ſhall be accordinglie.</p>
            <p>Thou goeſt forwards, ſpeaking of the reſtoration of that, whereof I ſay was immutable, and when thou haſt ſo done, thou ſayeſt we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn that ſpirit and way which cauſed the reſtitution; and ſo thou go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt on, paſsing judgement upon us, for what thou haſt conceived with thy own feigned imaginations, turn over and read once more what I have ſpoken, and ſee if truth doth not ſpeak plainlie its own meaning, and for that thou ſayeſt, here are the two ſpirits we tell on which were contrarie to the other; it is true, here they are the effects of the one, and the effects of the other, but as touching that ſpirit which guided
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168363:10"/>me in the denial of the ſpirit of meekneſs, and ſo in the exalted ſpirit, following my damned imaginations (if thou canſt ſee what plain words ſpeak) I have not caſt them upon you, but the waie by which I became poſſeſſed, I have declared, the end of which is a warning to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, (to ſpeak in the ſpirit of truth, deny me if thou canſt) and whereas thou ſayeſt, this thing being ſo, (ſpeaking of my deluſion) I was by you denied; I ſay, as to my perſon thy words are not, (witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by what is before ſpoken) but as touching the deluded ſpirit, read my words in the cloſe of my relation, and thereby reſt ſilent, for truth hath ſpoken, by which truth is ſet free.</p>
            <p>In thy 19. page thou repeateſt my words, where I ſay, that a ſhort time after my compliance with that ſpirit which entred into me by the obſervation of your practiſe; and then thou goeſt back to my ſecond page, and there in thy deceit thou borroweſt a compoſed lie of thy own to witneſs againſt this truth before ſpoken, but this lie is before laid open; and for that I ſaid the entrance of this unclean ſpirit was by the obſervation of your practiſe, which practiſe you declare to be from the ſpirit; it is true, I ſay the entrance was ſo, for the firſt entrance and work of deceit in me, after I came amongſt you, was my taking up of divers your practiſes in the imitation, the manner of which deceit I have (in its place) laid open; but as touching thoſe things thou haſt related, as the effects of this my ſaying, I denie, neither haſt thou any ground or reaſon for what thou haſt declared, but herein thou ſheweſt thy buſie minde, as one loving to pick quarrels, and watching to lay a ſnare before the truth, but now receive thy words as thy own; O thou ſhameleſs man! behold, amongſt men, who would have judged like unto thee?</p>
            <p>But to prove thy work of ſeeking to bring me into a confuſion, after thou haſt diſcovered thy vain minde in thy own by-waie, thou comeſt in thy 21. page to relate my words, which ſpeaks of my haſtie forward minde, and my own reſolved Covenant, by which in the fire of my zeal I was haſtilie carried forth before the true Light, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which things are true, and thy own confuſion being laid open, thou mayeſt read them ſo to be, for this haſtie forward mind, and this reſolved Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in this fire of zeal, was that by which I was overcome, and ſo took up things in the imitation, by which was received in that deluded ſpirit of which I have ſpoken, and ſo by degrees carried on, as I have ſaid, for a warning to others, that they alſo come not in the ſame exceſs, and yet how is it thou canſt appear in ſuch a witneſs, as to declare that what I have done is the work of the devil?</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:168363:11"/>
            <p>Thou goeſt on forwards with thy ſlanderous tongue in this thy falſe deſigne, and then in the cloſe of this page thou ſayeſt, I confeſs that when I came to the place where the Quakers were, ſhewing the holes I made in my thumbs, and telling of thoſe Lying-Wonders which I had been acting, many of the Quakers being there, all of them judged me with one conſent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and then ſayeſt thou in my 51. page I confeſs I was reſtored to a right underſtanding, and my life became a clear light, being guided in that obedience which was profeſſed by thoſe people: And then ſayeſt thou all this being my own confeſſion, yet I charge it upon a ſpirit which entred in me by the obſervation of your practiſe, and ſo thou goeſt on with thy refuge of lies, and then ask if ever ſuch a heap of confuſion and falſhood was uttered and ſigned for truth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but thoſe things being cleared alreadie, I ſhall let them paſs, onelie thou ſpeakeſt here of lying-wonders, which either diſcovers thy mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that what I have related are lies, otherwiſe they are the works of a lie wrought and witneſſed in me, by that deluded Spirit which led me forth in obedience to them; now if thy meaning be thus, then is thy witneſs true, but if thon meaneſt that my words are lies, then why is it that thou didſt not witneſs any one of them ſo to be, that ſo I might have ſeen my errors, but herein is thy ſubtiltie ſeen.</p>
            <p>Thou goeſt further, uttering much words to us for what thou haſt feigned in thy own imagination, and then in thy 23. page thou askeſt, Is there any in this City, but they are aſhamed to have a hand in ſuch a fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy thing? ſpeaking of what thy imagination hath conceived, which thou haſt caſt upon us, to which I anſwer, nay ſurely I judg there is not any but thy ſelf, and ſo receive theſe thy own words; conſider thy work in this thy confuſed thing, wherein thou haſt been forced ſo often to clear us, both with thy own words, and alſo with mine, of thoſe things thou haſt ſo often accuſed us of, and to the world declare thy ſelfe, whereof all the world cannot prove us guilty of theſe deceits, and open manifeſt inventions wrought by thee, further then to teſtifie againſt thee, and that ſpirit in thee and them, by which thou waſt helped in this thy workes of lyes and ſlanders, which are one, for the ſorcerer, the murther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and the lyer, is one ſpirit, ſo thou who haſt caſt theſe things upon us, which thy ſelfe doth teſtifie we denyed, and for that cauſe judgment was given, and a witneſſe for truth hath appeared to the world, let all men ſee by what ſpirit thou was led, Was there ever ſuch a thing done amongſt the people of God? had'ſt thou lived in the Apoſtles time, wouldeſt not thou have ſlandered the truth, &amp; the perſons of the Saints, with the act of <hi>Simon Magus</hi> (though it was much better then this of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:168363:11"/>thee, who fell the truth for a lye?) wouldſt not thou have charged the act of the inceſſious perſon upon the Apoſtles, and that of <hi>Annanias</hi> and <hi>Sephira,</hi> upon that ſpirit which appeared in them, and that of <hi>Judas</hi> upon Chriſt and his Diſciples, which is the like caſe, (all theſe being thy own acts, thou haſt appeared in their ſpirit, and then thou caſteſt thy Work upon us) and now had this been juſt dealeing to accuſe the innocent, or have you done here as you would be done unto, nay wouldeſt thou have the falſe witneſſes in this thy paper, caſt upon the innocent the abominations that is of thy ſelfe caſt upon us, this being the true caſe between thee and us, whoſe perſons thou haſt ſlandered, take it into conſideration, and let the light of Chriſt of which thou ſpeakeſt be Judg in you, whether you have kept the Royall Law, <hi>Do as you would be done unto,</hi> let him be wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs between us and you, whoſe ſpirit you have blaſphemed this daie, alſo let all the Judges of this Nation give their teſtimonie, and all that underſtand Law between man and man, if ſuch a witneſs deſerve not puniſhment ſuitable to his Slander, who would dare to be a witneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt others in things he never ſaw nor heard, though I am far from deſiring that any ſuch thing ſhould befall thee, but that thou mayeſt come to ſee thy unjuſt dealing after the manner of men, in that thou dareſt to act and witneſs ſuch contradictions and confuſions, as is in this thy book, and become a certain witneſs to that thou never ſaw nor heard, and ſo ſpeak thou knoweſt not what, and yet notwithſtanding thou haſt thus diſcovered the vain deceit of thy own minde, that thou ſhouldeſt for a cover thereof (to darken the underſtandings of the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) dare to appear with ſuch an appeal unto ſuch perſons of ſound judgement, and clear underſtanding, in reſpect of thoſe things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of thou ſpeakeſt as they are: O man! where art thou, if not beſide thy ſelf? Is thy underſtanding laid aſide? or art thou predominate in thy af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, that thou mighteſt boaſt in vanitie? was there ever ſuch a thing done by any that feared God? a moderate Heathen would have bluſhed thereat: But now how art thou falne? and how hath envie beſotted thee in this thy work? Theſe things, and much more, of which I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to ſpeak, haſt thou prepared a work for, and they for thy work: Did not <hi>Haman</hi> inſult againſt <hi>Mordicai,</hi> and ſo brought the evil upon himſelf which was deſigned for <hi>Mordicai?</hi> and is it not ſo between thee and us? haſt thou not laid a ſnare before the truth to intrap us, and then prepared a ſcourge? but now thou haſt brought that evil upon thy ſelf, which thou intendeſt for us, and here is thy deceit made manifeſt.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:168363:12"/>
            <p>Having thus diſcovered thy uncleanneſs and work of a lie, thou goeſt on in thy 23. page with my words, where I ſay, that I had a clear un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of what your Miniſtry held forth, and a right knowledge of your belief and practiſe before I complied with you, and then ſayeſt thou, here I adde another lie to cover the former, and ſo I go about to clear you again; to which I anſwer, as I have cleared alreadie, what I have ſpoken is true, &amp; thy deceit being laid open, thou mayeſt read them ſo to be; have I all along in my book diſcovered the truth of things, that thoſe ſcandals which have paſſed abroad might be ſeen and witneſſed againſt? Nay, couldſt thou have done more thy ſelf, had the caſe been thy own? and yet for all this goeſt thou about to reproach and revile me for that I have thus done, and that by turning truth into lies, and ſo make a ſcorn and deriſion of the work of the ſpirit? and yet doeſt thou juſtifie thy deed as though thou waſt thus guided by the ſpirit, let all thoſe of whom thou calleſt to witneſs between thee and me, whoſe eyes are in their heads, bear witneſs in truth without partialitie between us, and then ſhall they not ſee thy follie? yea, alſo read thy ſelf, and thy own condemnation, that ſo thou maiſt, for the time to come, learn more wiſdome, and not dare to appear in ſuch a fair ſhow, as though in love to truth, whenas thou makeſt thy ſelf manifeſt to be a devourer of the truth.</p>
            <p>In thy 26. page thou confeſſeſt thy ſelf, that I tell the occaſion how I came to be loſt in my underſtanding, and ſo diſtracted and confuſed in mind, and then thou goeſt on repeating my words, which diſcovers the occaſion to be another thing then your perſons, and yet the whole ſcope of thy book is intended to make people believe that I caſt it upon your perſons; and again thou acknowledgeſt that what I have here diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, is for the clearing of truth, and yet in thy confuſion thou cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt this ſubtiltie, but if ſo, then thou art ſubtiltie, for that thou denieſt not by theſe thy words, but that it is for the clearing of truth; was not deceit uppermoſt when thou appeareſt in this work, and thy underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding covered with darkneſs? yea ſurelie, and ſo it was; and here that judgment, of which thou ſpeakeſt, is witneſſed out of thy own mouth to be thy own; for if it was the true ſpirituall Light which let me to ſee my darkneſs, as I have ſaid it was, and that it would have guided me out of the works of the fleſh, ſelf-thoughts and imaginations; and if the cauſe why I turned from that Light was my natural forward minde and reſolutions (as it was) and ſo lead forth in obedience to a covenant of my own before the true light, by which the Light of the Sun was dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and a ſhape formed in the likeneſs of the true light, whereby de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:168363:12"/>got power to do thoſe filthie things; and if I was reſtored again by the true Light (as I was) and ſo guided in the obedience which is profeſſed by you; if theſe things are true (as they are) then let all, unto whom thou appealeſt, wherein there is the leaſt meaſure of honeſtie, judg righteouſlie between us, and ſee if that the blaſphemie, lies and ſlanders, and abominable confuſions, which thou caſt upon us, be not in truth thy own, who all along in thy book hath gone about to defile and ſlander the true Light of the ſpirit of God, under a pretence of clearing the truth; but receive thy own words as they are thine; canſt thou behold thy confuſion and not be aſhamed? Doſt thou ſcoff at me for calling my work the <hi>Foot out of the Snare,</hi> and declare againſt it, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it the <hi>Foot in the Snare?</hi> Art not thou aſhamed at thy envie againſt the innocent? Is this that innocencie of which thou boaſteſt on? haſt thou not caſt a ſtone at us? but is it not falne back upon thy ſelf? Is this thy <hi>Foot in the Snare?</hi> then conſider thy work, and ſee thy end, for for that thou haſt enſnared thy ſelf, and ſo receive thy own, canſt thou ſay and unſay, accuſe and excuſe and all in one thing, and yet witneſſe all for truth? who would have fed upon miſchief like thee? doſt thou believe that all are ſo blinde, as ſome who are led by you, to believe all for truth that thou ſpeakeſt without examination? Or doſt thou think that wiſdome and light is whollie excluded (as thou ſayeſt) and true judgment whollie reſpected, then mighteſt thou think with thy words, that thy lies and deceits might have paſſed without reproof, and thou cover thy ſelf therewith as with a garment, but the Lord is riſen, and riſing, and the light is come, and the day ſpringing from on high, is viſiting his people, and all works of darkneſſe muſt come to judgment; and for thoſe deſpiſed people of vvhom thou ſpeakeſt, vvho have none to take their part in the earth, I refuſe to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in enmitie againſt them, but for that I ſee you Builders have led them forth into bondage, and have ſpoiled vvhat is their libertie; have I ſpoken; my vvord ſhall ſtand in truth? But for <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> I denie, and all vvho are in their vvorſhip, and that I ovvne vvhich is one in Spirit and Povver, vvhich is no lie; but that Lamb of God and his light whereof thou ſpeakeſt, in whom there is no ſin, and for the liar it is thy ſelf, witneſſe the light in thy own conſcience, and divers thy own words, which from that light thou waſt conſtrained to ſpeak in the juſtifying of that truth which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in me, and with that light art thou comprehended, by which thy ground and thy end is ſeen, with the depth of thy own deceit, and though we are ſtrangers in ſpirit, and enmitie is gotten in between us,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168363:13"/>yet that arm of the Lord is ſeen (whereof thou ſpeakeſt) gathering his ſheep which have been ſcattered upon the mountains this cloudie dark day, who reſtores the lame, ſtrengthens the feeble, and carries the lambs in his boſome, becauſe they are his own, glorie be to his Name for ever, and as for worſhip, adding to, or altering from what was in his Saints, by the ſame light in my meaſure which was in them I denie; and alſo for thoſe Vinedreſſers, who ſtand up in defence of themſelves againſt the heir, who is coming to call for fruit, whoſe Vineyard brings forth pride, vain-glory, and reſpect of perſons, love of the world, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie thereto, creature worſhips, and one which is not of God, I ſay as for all ſuch I denie, and their worſhip, neither have I pleaded in the leaſt for them, but for thoſe and their fruits which are out of time, out of the ſpirit of this world, and as for greatneſſe of rage in me againſt ſuch whoſe lives are thus hid with Chriſt in God, it hath not appeared in me, neither dare I to appear in ſuch a work, for that I know there is a ſeed, whoſe Name is perfection, whichis riſen and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to utter his voice, to the ends of the earth, that he might eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh his own Name for a light to his people <hi>Iſrael:</hi> This do I ſee and know, and for that cauſe do I reſt ſilent; and theſe are thoſe of whom it is true, they have loſt their Kindred, the pleaſure of the earth, and the delights therein is brought to their end, they have ſeen a ceſſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of time, and they are laid much lower then the loweſt of men; and for this cauſe are they worthy, who follow the Lamb whereſoever he goeth, and in his life they ſhall live, yet ſuch there are of whom thou art not known, though not altogether, but for the Potters of the earth they ſhall be daſhed in pieces, therefore, Oh ye Sons of men! Why will ye not turn to the Rock from whence ye were hewn, and to that pit out of which ye were digged, that ye might draw from thence the freſh Springs of that Fountain, which giveth to his people eternal life. I am a Fountain ſet open for ſin and for uncleanneſſe, come unto me all ye who are wearie and heavie laden that ye might be watered with the dew of heaven, and ye ſhall finde reſt for your ſoules, my yoak is eaſie and my burthen is light, but for ſuch who are gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together in a confederacie againſt my Name, when my wrath is waxed hot, I will ariſe in my furie, and recompence you according to your work.</p>
            <p>Thou beginneſt in thy 31. page with a word to me, diſcovering what I ſaid to divers friends, that I did put forth what I have done to clear the truth profeſſed by you, from many ſcandals caſt upon it, through my means, and then ſaveſt thou, that truth by you profeſſed is a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:168363:13"/>againſt me for ever, that I have not ſought to clear it, but I have ſought my own, and alſo that I have cauſed the truth to be blaſphemed above all that ever was before me in this Generation ſince the time of his appearance, who is the Light of the world; and for that end I have gone to conſult with the greateſt enemies to that truth profeſſed by you that are in the Nation. Now as touching all what thou haſt here ſpoken, I utterlie denie; for did <hi>I</hi> ſo ſpeak to friends my words are true, for that I have ſpoken in much plainneſs to that end, witneſſed and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by all what I have before ſpoken. And whereas thou ſayeſt, that truth profeſſed by you witneſſes againſt me that I have not ſo done; <hi>I</hi> ſay, by that truth of which thou ſpeakeſt, <hi>I</hi> denie thy words, and that from whence thy words came; and this is a Standard from the Lord in defence againſt thee, and the depth of thy back-ſliding work alſo; and now ſhall the people mourn becauſe of thee, who hath ſo much appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in defence of the truth, and yet art found thy ſelf ſmothered in ſuch filth, as thou haſt here appeared in; a man of unclean lips and defiled tongue, ſhall not all, in whom there is the leaſt meaſure of truth, bear witneſs againſt thee? Yea ſurelie they ſhall ſo if they appear for truth (as I have ſaid) without partialitie: And now is it, that it is thy ſelf, who hath ſought thy own, and not the good of that whereof thou ſpeakeſt, but hath brought a ten-fold greater reproach upon that truth profeſſed by thy ſelf, then can be witneſſed I have, and for that thou ſayeſt I conſulted with the greateſt enemies of truth in the Nation, I denie thee thou bodie of deceit, how is it (as I have ſaid) thou dareſt to ſpeak what thou neither ſaw nor heard, yet not ſo alone, but alſo foretold, and (as I have ſaid) witneſſed to thy face, when privilie thou wenteſt about to enquire of one, if the Anabaptiſt, or any other, had not a confederacie with me in what I have done: Is this the work of ſimplicitie? Nay ſurelie it is not, I ſay I did not conſult with any, neither was there any addition or exchange of one word but what is my own, all which I yet own, and am fully ſatisfied in being witneſſed therein by truth, onlie for that I was perſwaded to ingage thoſe Miniſters, and ſo have brought them under the reach of thy Snare, when in truth, as to them, were it not for that miſtake, they ſtood free in what they have there done, and alſo for that I was overcome in ſuch a great miſtake, and carried aſide by vanitie in that deed of engaging them: I ſay, onlie for theſe things I have much been diſquieted, and it doth repent me that I have appeared therein, but for the reſt it was not mine but ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whoſe work ſhall abide, and for this (to prevent thy former ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpirit) I declare that not one of thoſe Miniſters, or any other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:168363:14"/>who would have ſtored me up herein, I ſay, not one of them have the leaſt knowledge of what I have here done, neither ſhall it be known to any one of them until it be publiſhed to the ſight of the world; and now for that evil thou haſt declared to come upon me, fear poſſeſſeth me not, but I bear with thy weakneſs therein; yet for the reproach it is thy own, and for that thou ſayeſt I gainſayed and turned into fables, and believed lies; it is true, great was my follie, I did ſo; yet in thy meaning thou art denied, for they were not peremptorie acts, on purpoſe to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the ſpirit of God, but I was guided therein through miſtake, in much love towards God, the manner of which miſtake I have plainlie laid open, and let all be warned thereby, for truth changeth not; and for the Prieſts making me their refuge there was no ſuch thing, for I was guided of my ſelf to go unto them, and being wel known to ſome of them, they gave credit to my words (as touching thoſe things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of their names were intended) though they ſaw not my work, which was one, and the ſame, as though they had ſeen it, for the thing it ſelfe being onlie a Relation, and no diſcoverie of judgment: Did I make known in few words what I had declared in many words? and were thoſe few believed? then was there as good faith in believing the truth of the one, as the truth of the other, but that thy contentious mind muſt be at work.</p>
            <p>Thou goeſt forwards, ſaying, Was I brought to ſee my ſin, and yet I heard nothing of the Goſpel? I ſay, I have not ſpoken that I heard no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Goſpel; but if thou here meaneſt that I did not hear any thing of the Goſpel, then haſt thou ſpoken thou knoweſt not what, for I have heard and ſeen the Miniſtrie of the Goſpel, and the power thereof; but for my believing of lies, and gainſaying the truth, I ſay, by the Spirit of truth, is that Spirit from whence thou haſt ſo ſpoken de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied; and had I dealt with <hi>Abel</hi> my Brother like <hi>Cain,</hi> or turned back into <hi>Aegypt</hi> like <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re,</hi> then would their judgment have reſted upon me; but (as I have before ſpoken) fear poſſeſſeth me not, my conſcience bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing me witneſs in the ſight of God; but were it ſo, I had dealt with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel</hi> like as did <hi>Cain,</hi> yet nevertheleſſe the day of my viſitation had not been over, neither had the Law power over me any longer then I had been a ſervant unto corruption; for when <hi>Cain</hi> had killed his brother, there was yet mercie if that he encreaſed not in his uncleanneſs, as the ſpirit ſaith unto him, <hi>If thou doeſt well, thou ſhalt have thy reward, if o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, then ſin lyeth at the doore:</hi> Now where either of us are found in ungodlie deeds, the Lord rebuke us, but for thy railing Accuſation, and turning truth into lables, and ſo making lies thy refuge, thou art come
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:168363:14"/>up for proof before the Lord, by whoſe ſpirit thy ſpirit it is which is ſavoured and tried, unto whom thy voice is known and witneſſed againſt, as being the voice of a roaring Lyon, and a ravenous Bear, and not from the ſpirit of the Lord; and now is it that thou art the man who hath enſnared thy ſelf, and brought a prejudice upon the truth, for that thou haſt conſulted with the Beaſt and the falſe Prophet, and ſo thou art become the devourer; and here is <hi>Judas</hi> and the chief Prieſts, and their falſe Witneſſes; and here are the lies and the confuſions, leaſt ſimple mindes ſhould be led with a lie through the ſome of the Frogs.</p>
            <p>And now art thou made manifeſt in this thy work, as one who is gone aſtray out of the plain way of the true ſhepherd, and ſo art become a ſtranger to the flocks of his Companions; wherefore learn hence to ſtay at home, and receive teachings from that true ſhepherd, that thou mayeſt know his voice, and follow him, who gives to his choſen eternal life, who is the Light of the world, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nlightneth everie one that cometh into the world; whoſe judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is true upon his enemies, and whoſe condemnation abideth for ever.</p>
            <p>Wherefore a Word to thoſe three ſorts of people (of whom thou ſpeakeſt) who may be concerned in what I have done.</p>
            <p>To the firſt ſort, Thoſe who have received the Light of Chriſt, whoſe eye is in their head, who are come to any meaſure of the Annointing, who are joyned in the Election; to you I ſay, is this deliverance from the bonds of iniquitie, and from that Captivitie wherein you were carried aſide from the peaceable union and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of the eternal love; to you is this deliverance given, that your lives might ſhew forth the life and death of him, by whom you were called, to the praiſe and glorie of his grace, and for which end he have given his Light, that with it ye might ſee all what is darkneſs, all what loveth and maketh a lie, all what is falne from God; that ye might comprehend the depth of Satan, and all the ſecret bonds of iniquitie; and here is the Rock <hi>Chriſt,</hi> before whom all ſhall fall, and this Rock, this Light is your defence, in whom abiding, the falſe Prophet, the Beaſt and the Deceiver is ſeen and rejected, and not onlie in your ſelves, but alſo in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of thoſe in whom he doth appear; wherefore ſtand faſt in that libertie whereunto you are called, that your obedience being
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:168363:15"/>wrought in that faith which giveth life, ye might in the end obtain the Crown.</p>
            <p>To the ſecond ſort, Thoſe who in their hearts are convinced of the way of truth, but finding it ſtraight to their carnall pleaſures and profits, not loving the truth more then the world, but taking pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs, and ſerving and loving the creature more then the Creator; to you I ſay, watch while as yet ye have time, and pleaſe not your ſelves with vanitie and the work of lies, that ye ſtumble not in the way which leadeth to life, and ſo he ſwallowed up of corruption; for if while you ſeek to be juſtified by Chriſt you are found in the tranſgreſſion, and ſo fruſtrate the Grace of God, there remains no more ſacrifice for ſin; wherefore call to mind your former condition, when you were ſtrangers to the true Faith, and ſo kept in bondage under the Law, and learn from him who is true, to receive the love and grace made known, that ye might walk worthie of that calling whereunto you are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and ſhew forth the praiſe of him who hath opened your eyes, and give you to ſee that darkneſs by which (in times paſt) you were ſold under ſin, wherefore in love receive admonition, that ſo being redeemed out of the world, ye might grow up in him who is the Fountain of eternal life, and be brought to ſee the glory of the Fathers love, <hi>This then is the meſſage that we have heard of him, and declare unto you, that God is light, in him is no darkneſſe at all, If we ſay that we have fellowſhip with him, and walk in darkneſſe, we lye, and do not the truth, John</hi> 1.5.6.</p>
            <p>To the third ſort, ſuch who have a ſimplicity in them, and a love to the truth, and the way thereof, and would walk in it did they know it, but are yet kept in blindneſſe and darkneſſe by their blind Guides, who take advantage by theſe works of the devil, lies, and ſlanders, to thicken the Vail, and ſtrengthen the bonds, thereby to keep them from the light of life, and the way of peace, and ſo in the way of deſtruction for their corrupt ends, I ſay, for you who are in this caſe, out of the knowledg of God, his light, and life, which is ſalvation, for you have I much been diſquieted, being ſenſible of your condition; but as I have already endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to remove that prejudice, which may attend you by thoſe falſe concluſions, which have appeared in enmity to what I have done, though I may not ſay directly in enmity to you: And as I
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:168363:15"/>have diſcovered the truth of that cauſe and end for which I have appeared to the world, which thing is not that thereby ye ſhould be affrighted from the truth, but when received, that ye might give heed to abide in that by which you were convinced, that ſo ye may not run into the ſame exceſſe, ſo alſo that ye may not be overcome with that ſpirit of deceit, and ſtabliſhed in that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt mind in which you have been kept and guided out of the wayes of truth, I ſay, that ye may not be overcome (by any work of mine) to abide in this darkneſſe. That God who is a Spirit, is not divided, but his Name is one, and this God cannot be known by any wayes of worſhip, or practiſe amongſt men, but by his Son, who is that Spirit and Life, by which the Election of God are redeemed out of all corruption, out of all wayes and works of the fleſh, into a ſpiritual Union with that God who is the Father of Spirits, and cannot be worſhipped, but by and in the Spirit, and therefore is it ſpoken in Scripture concerning Chriſt, <hi>That for this purpoſe was he made manifeſt, to deſtroy the works of the devil, John</hi> 3.8. Now where is this manifeſtation of Chriſt to be found, for the deſtruction of the works of the fleſh, or of the devil, but in faln man, where the works of the unclean ſpirit are wrought? and from whence they do proceed? and for which cauſe was that promiſe given? <hi>That the Seed of the Woman, ſhould break the head of the Serpent,</hi> which Seed is Chriſt, he was born under the Law, to redeem them that were under the Law; he was brought forth into the world, and made a ſhew of them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly, triumphing over them in it, he ſuffered in his body the death of the Croſſe, and after that time, appointed of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he was raiſed out of the grave, cloathed with immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and received up into glory; and now he hath given gifts unto men, he hath diſperſed his ſeed, he hath given of his ſpirit, he hath made known his light, in, and unto all the children of men, that by, and with this his manifeſtation and diſcovery of himſelf, his eternal love and grace, I ſay, that by, and with this, men might ſee, and underſtand, and receive power for the deſtruction of the body of corruption, and for the ſervice and worſhip of God in ſpirit, in obedience to a living faith; and now let men profeſſe what they will, and aſſemble themſelves in what way, and under what manner ſoever, yet if they receive not their Miniſtery from
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:168363:16"/>this Spirit Chriſt Jeſus revealed in all, and follow him who is the Lamb of God, who taketh away the ſin, that they may receive power from him to be redeemed out of ſin, I ſay, if they receive not their teſtimony from this Spirit of Jeſus, to live therein, they ſhall not, neither can they ever come to ſee that eternal love, that peace and union, which is in God through Chriſt Jeſus, the portion of the faithful, in him who is perfect: Wherefore I ſay unto you all, who take pleaſure in your uncleanneſs, and ſport your ſelves with your ſecret abominations, now in the day time, and yet boaſt of your Redeemer, I ſay unto you repent, leſt that day come upon you unawares, in which there is no time or ſpace for repentance, and look unto him who is the light of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and is given for a light to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> that they might ſee and return unto him, who is the Redeemer out of all ſin, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoreth the breaches, and buildeth up the walls of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and giveth life unto his two Witneſſes who have lain ſlain in the ſtreets thereof, that they might go forth, and declare the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Goſpel of peace.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
